The Loneliest Whale: The Search for 52 is a
documentary film directed by Joshua Zeman.
THE LONELIEST WHALE is a cinematic quest to find the “52 Hertz Whale,” which scientists believe has spent its
entire life in solitude calling out at a frequency that is different from any other whale.
As the film embarks on this engrossing journey, audiences will explore what this whale’s lonely plight
can teach us — not just about our changing relationship to the oceans, but to each other.
Executive Produced with Leonardo DiCaprio and Adrian Grenier.
The 52-hertz whale, colloquially referred to as 52 Blue, is an individual whale of unidentified species that calls at the
unusual frequency of 52 hertz in the north Pacific Ocean between Aleutian and Kodiak Islands to the California coast.
The whale itself has never been sighted: it has only been heard via hydrophones, but its call has been detected
since the late 1980s in a pattern that matches the migration of the blue whale and the fin whale.
Those species call at 10 to 39 Hz and 20 Hz respectively.
Described as the "world's loneliest whale", it appeared to be the only
individual emitting a whale call at this frequency.
However, recordings of a second 52-hertz whale, heard elsewhere at the
same time, have been sporadically found since 2010.
52 Hz is roughly equivalent to the musical note G#1, which is the 12th lowest key on a standard 88-key
piano keyboard, or the 4th finger position on the lowest string (E1) of a double bass.
The film explores themes of ocean, whale, underwater.